The gold standard to measure your VO2 max
is going to be in a laboratory
with a metabolic cart.
You can get this stuff
in various equations.
You can use any of your
fitness technologies.
I will strongly encourage you though
that if you care about this number,
if it's possible,
and it may not be,
spend a couple of hundred dollars
and get this actually
tested in the laboratory.
The data are quite clear, at this point.
I have not yet seen really any standard
over the counter fitness technology
that gets an accurate
number of your VO2 max
when the number gets high
and particularly for people
who are already fairly fit.
If you're VO2 max is really low,
it might give you a decent number.
But for folks that are kind
of moderate to highly trained,
it's just really challenging
to get an appropriate
estimate from a watch
or a ring or things like that.
Perhaps, those will improve in the future.
In fact, I quite expect them to.
But as of now,
the margin of error is a
little bit too high for me
to be comfortable with when
you care about accuracy.
If you're trying to just get
a global sense, they're fine.
In fact, if you want to do that,
you can use any number
of absolutely free estimate equations.
Examples of this would include
something like a two-minute step test
where you would take your heart rate,
step up and down on a very
small box, say 12 inches or so.
You do that continuously for two minutes
and then measure your
heart rate at the end.
You can enter that score into an equation
and get an estimate of your VO2 max.
Those are scientifically
validated methodologies.
The 12-minute test ends up being
something like a mile and a half run.
So you could simply, in fact,
you could do this if you'd like, as well.
Run a mile and a half as fast as you can.
Take that time.
Enter it into equation
and get an estimate.
If you have that time as
well as your heart rate,
you can enter it in as well
and get a more accurate picture.
And so again, all of these are close.
We call these sub-maximal estimates
because they are that,
they're not the direct measure.
So I would encourage you, again,
if at all possible to
actually go into a laboratory
and get this measured.
In addition, if you do
something like that,
you can get a bunch of other metrics
you can't get with some of
these estimated equations,
like what percentage of fat
versus carbohydrate you're using,
your anaerobic and lactate thresholds,
your maximum ventilation
so how much total air
you can bring in and out,
and a bunch of other stuff that
we talked about on the show
and we'll get into in a second.
Again, if you don't have access
to any of that, that's fine.
Use any of those other free
or extremely low cost options
and you'll get yourself pretty close.
Our next "I" is interpretation.
So sticking with heart rate and VO2 max,
as I mentioned a little bit earlier,
resting heart rate will go
down as you improve fitness,
but your maximum heart rate
will not really change.
In fact, if anything, it will be reduced
because you're a little bit older.
And so to state it one more time,
there's no real association
between highly fit people
and their maximum heart
rate, and unfit people.
So it's not a metric
that we should be overly
concerned about of,
you know, where is your
maximum heart rate.
It is relevant to, again,
your stroke volume,
but the heart rate itself is
not going to tell you that much.
So not something to be concerned about.
Your resting heart rate though,
or your heart rate at any given
intensity is very important.
So if you're going to be running,
say at a standard pace,
say seven miles per hour
and your heart rate at
seven miles per hour
was 150 beats per minute
and now a couple of months later,
your heart rate at the exact same speed
is now 115 beats per minute.
That would represent a
significant improvement
in cardiovascular fitness.
Stroke volume would be much higher.
And because of that,
that allows your heart rate to come down.
Resting heart rate is a similar story.
I'm giving you a little
bit of context here.
And the reason this is top of mind
is because there's a hummingbird
that lives in my backyard
and my wife and kids look
at it every single day
and they get so excited.
They call her mom's little helper.
They named it Squirt, actually.
And so they get really excited
when this little hummingbird
is flying back there
'cause it's super fast.
Hummingbirds have a resting heart rate
of something like 1200 beats per minute.
It's absolutely insane.
So you're talking about
putting an order of magnitude
on top of almost a human
maximum heart rate.
You contrast that to a
larger animal like a giraffe,
an elephant or a blue whale
and you're talking about a heart rate
of something like five
to six beats per minute.
And so humans, of course,
are somewhere in between.
If you were technically to Google this,
you might see something like
a normal resting heart rate
is 60 to 100 beats per minute.
I'm here to tell you,
I cannot fathom a situation
in which somebody's resting heart rate
is over 80 beats per minute
and they are healthy.
And I absolutely would not think that
that would happen to somebody
who's performing at their maximum.
In fact, I even will tell you,
this is off the record,
this is not the science,
this is me and my professional opinion.
Even a resting a heart rate of 60 or so,
particularly in a man is...
That's catching my eye.
I would like to see most folks probably
in the forties to fifties,
somewhere in the range.
Again, you might be fine at 60,
but getting a much above 60
is quite a bit high.
I also personally tell you,
I've worked with plenty of athletes,
specifically in this case,
several UFC fighters
whose resting heart rates
were in the low forties,
if not high thirties.
So 37, 38, 40, things like this.
And so that's the lowest
I have personally seen.
That said, there are classic stories
of plenty of endurance athletes.
You're talking about elite cyclists
and cross country skiers and
marathon runners and such
who are in the low thirties.
Lowest I'm aware of
is the legendary cyclist, Miguel Indurain,
having a resting heart rate
of 28 beats per minute.
As far as I can tell,
that's the lowest ever reported
in the scientific literature.
Though please, if you've
seen any lower, let me know.
I'm sure there are plenty
of stories of anecdotes
of people in personal
training records and stuff
who think they're lower.
But if you've ever seen anything
verified scientifically,
I would love to see that.
Interpreting your VO2 max is
more interesting in my opinion
'cause there's a lot of components to it.
And so in order to truly understand this,
let's talk about how we
calculate VO2 max to begin with.
The easiest way in my opinion
is to think about VO2 max
equals your cardiac output
multiplied by what's called
your AVO2 difference.
Now, as I've stated,
cardiac output is simply
your stroke volume
multiplied by your heart rate.
So if we were to combine
this entire thing,
we would say your heart rate
multiplied by your stroke volume,
which says, okay,
how much blood am I getting out per pump?
How many pumps am I getting?
And I multiply that by what's
called your AVO2 difference.
Now the A stands for arterial,
V stands for venous,
and the O2 is oxygen.
So what literally this means
is what's the difference
in oxygen concentrations
between the arterial
side and the venous side?
Remember, arteries generally
go away from your heart,
which means they're going
to exercising tissue,
and veins come back.
And so what we're really
looking at is saying,
okay, how much blood,
how much oxygen's in the blood
when it leaves the heart,
this is going to be the
highest concentration
of oxygen possible,
and how much is in the
blood when it comes back
having passed through muscle?
This then directly tells you
how much oxygen your tissue
extracted in the process.
So to give you some numbers here,
to make this easy,
these are not accurate,
just representing the math here.
If you had a hundred molecules of oxygen
that left your heart
and went into your quadriceps,
and then once it's gone
through the capillaries
that surround all the muscles
and tissues and fibers
in your quadriceps
and it went in as a hundred
and then it came back out the other side
and went back to the heart
and lungs to be re-oxygenated,
well, if it went in at a hundred
and came out as 75,
the difference between the
arterial and the venous side
is a hundred minus 75,
which would give you a score of 25.
Now what that means, and again,
I'm using those round
numbers to make this simple.
You've extracted now 25% of the oxygen
that came in your system.
You only got 25% of it out.
That's not a very good score.
You want that number,
because it's a multiplier,
to be as high as possible.
So if a hundred goes in, I
don't want 75 coming out,
I want zero coming out.
Let's say maybe you got 10 out.
So now a hundred went in, 10 came out.
You extracted 90% of the oxygen
that was available to you
and got to bring it into muscle
and use it for everything
we talked about earlier.
And so now your AVO2 difference is 90,
much higher than 25.
So we get to multiply that
by our cardiac output,
which brings our VO2 max even higher.
The easiest way to think about VO2 max
is to use what's called
the thick equation.
VO2 max, according to the thick equation
is your heart rate,
in other words, how many beats per minute,
multiplied by your stroke volume,
how much blood coming out per pump,
multiplied by what's called
your AVO2 difference.
To be perfectly honest with you,
the AVO2 difference numbers
are difficult to convey over audio only.
So I'm going to spend most of our time
on the other side of the equation.
When it comes time to
interpreting your VO2 max numbers,
there's a lot of charts
and papers you can use.
We'll provide some of those
in the show notes for you.
I want to give you some numbers though
to give you rough context.
Typically, we think about VO2 max
in what's called a relative term.
Now scientists and people
that are more advanced in this field
might like to use the absolute versions.
Depending on the scenario,
that might make more sense.
But for now, let's just
stick to the relative.
What that means is
how many milliliters of oxygen
are you using
per kilogram of body weight
per minute?
So you'll see them expressed
as things like your VO2
max is 50 milliliters
per kilogram
per minute.
So 50 milliliters of oxygen
per kilogram of body weight
per minute.
You can kind of think about VO2 max
almost on a scale of zero to 100.
And so the average person
that would kind of say,
walk out of my classroom
somewhat moderately
trained, male or female,
that's you know, in the
neighborhood of 170 pounds
or 70 kilos, something like that,
is probably going to
have a VO2 max around,
you know, 35 to 45 milliliters
per kilogram per minute.
Something in that range.
If you fall below 18 milliliters
per kilogram per minute,
you're probably crossing
below the threshold
of what we call independence.
For women, that's about 15 or 16,
which means it's very
difficult to live independently
and by yourself
because your fitness is so low
going through basic activities
of daily living become challenging.
So what I'd like to share with you
is not only the normative values,
but also the highest we've ever seen
in terms of VO2 max, cardiac
output and stroke volume.
Now there's so much data on VO2 max,
we can actually break this down by age
and by sex,
in really specific numbers.
So if you know your exact age,
you can go ahead and look
these up in these charts.
But I'll give you a couple
again just to give you a ballpark.
Let's say you were a female
between 40 and 49-years-old
and your VO2 max was 28.
That would put you as what we
consider to be below average.
If you wanted to go from
below average to average,
you'd have to go into the 32
to 36 milliliters per kilogram range.
If you wanted to go all the way to elite,
tell me what's the best ever,
you'd be needing to surpass the mark
of 47 milliliters per kilogram per minute.
Any of you that are maybe older,
let's go ahead and jump way down.
Let's say you are 71-years-old,
again, talking about a
71-year-old female here.
Below 18, you know,
you're still above that
line of independence,
but it would still be considered low.
You would really want to be
looking at something like 22 to 24
to be considered above average
and then really over 36
to be considered elite.
Now I know my friend, Peter
Attia, likes to tell people
he wants them to be considered elite
in at least the decade
before their actual age,
if not two decades before.
And that's a phenomenal
way to think about it.
So just as that example,
if you were that incredibly ambitious
and vigorous 71-year-old,
elite for you would be 36 milliliters
per kilogram per minute.
The decade before, again
60 to 69, that would be 40.
But if you wanted to be that extra person
to get that double gold stamp from Peter,
you'd want to be above 46.
So the difference was going from 36 to 46
would give you that elite category
for two decades younger than you.
For the men, it's a similar story.
You just add a little
bit of the numbers to it.
So a male who is say
between 50 and 59-years-old,
above average would be 36
to 40 milliliters per kilogram per minute.
And you'd need to be above 50
to be considered elite at that age.
Now, in my personal opinion,
I kind of like to say there's
no excuse to be under 50
unless you're over 50,
meaning you have no reason
to be having a VO2 max of lower than 50
unless you're over 50-years-old.
And even then, 50 to 60,
I don't want you anywhere near below 50.
So that's a nice number to go after.
We'll also talk about in a
second how changeable that is
and how much it responds to
various types of training.
And so it's going to give
you a little bit of hope.
You have some room to move there
and it will respond to your training.
And so there's some light
at the end of the tunnel.
If you're looking at those numbers
and you've had a VO2 max done recently
and you're thinking,
"Oh my gosh, I am way below
what Andy said there,"
that's fine.
You still have within your
capabilities to change that.
[music]